<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[prime[31] blog - Unity tips, tricks and random thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.prime31.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.prime31.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-06T19:54:10-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.prime31.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Desaro]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ConstantsGeneratorKit: Killing Naked Strings So You Don't Have To]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.prime31.com/constants-generator-kit"/>
    <updated>2014-12-05T19:12:12-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.prime31.com/constants-generator-kit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Killing naked strings? What the heck does that even mean? If you have ever worked on a large project with a medium-to-large sized team you will know exactly what I am talking about. How many times have you seen brittle code like this <code>GameObject.FindWithTag( "SpawnPoint" )</code> or this <code>someGameObject.tag == "Enemy"</code>? Those strings are naked and afraid and they will come back to haunt you later.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modeling 2D Water With Springs: Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.prime31.com/water2d-part2"/>
    <updated>2014-12-01T22:09:42-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.prime31.com/water2d-part2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In part 1, all the groundwork for setting up the water simulation was laid. We have springs attached to the top verts of the water plane, which always want to remain in their neutral position. Once a force is applied to the springs they will oscillate back and forth based on the dampening and tension constants that are passed in.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modeling 2D Water With Springs: Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.prime31.com/water2d-part1"/>
    <updated>2014-11-28T17:16:05-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.prime31.com/water2d-part1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Water is one of those things in the world of game development that can range anywhere from incredibly simple to insanely complex. Your first attempt at making water might not be anything more than a transparent quad. Compare a solution like that with something like the water as seen in <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=Assassin%27s+Creed+IV:+Black+Flag+water&amp;tbm=isch">Assassin&rsquo;s Creed IV: Black Flag</a> or <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=bioshock+water&amp;tbm=isch">Bioshock</a> to get an idea of how far it can be taken.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
